<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- name="GENERATOR" content="github.com/mmarkdown/mmark Mmark Markdown Processor - mmark.miek.nl" -->
<rfc version="3" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-dkim-replay-problem-00" submissionType="IETF" category="info" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" indexInclude="true" consensus="true">

<front>
<title abbrev="DKIM Replay Problem">DKIM Replay Problem Statement</title><seriesInfo value="draft-ietf-dkim-replay-problem-00" stream="IETF" status="informational" name="Internet-Draft"></seriesInfo>
<author fullname="Weihaw Chuang"><organization>Google, Inc.</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>weihaw@google.com</email>
</address></author><author fullname="Dave Crocker"><organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
</address></author><author fullname="Allen Robinson"><organization>Google, Inc.</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>arobins@google.com</email>
</address></author><author fullname="Bron Gondwana"><organization>Fastmail Pty Ltd</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>brong@fastmailteam.com</email>
</address></author><date/>
<area>Application</area>
<workgroup>DKIM</workgroup>
<keyword>DKIM</keyword>
<keyword>Replay</keyword>

<abstract>
<t>DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM, RFC6376) permits claiming some
responsibility for a message by cryptographically associating a domain name
with the message.  For data covered by the cryptographic signature, this also
enables detecting changes made during transit. DKIM survives basic email
relaying.  In a Replay Attack, a recipient of a DKIM-signed message re-posts
the message to other recipients,while retaining the original, validating
signature, and thereby leveraging the reputation of the original signer. This
document discusses the resulting damage to email delivery, interoperability,
and associated mail flows.  A significant challenge to mitigating this
problem is that it is difficult for receivers to differentiate between
legitimate forwarding flows and a DKIM Replay Attack.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction"><name>Introduction</name>

<dl>
<dt>DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM):</dt>
<dd><t>Defined in <xref target="RFC6376"></xref> is a well-established email protocol.</t>
</dd>
</dl>
<t>DKIM permits a person, role, or organization to claim some responsibility for
a message by associating a domain name <xref target="RFC1034"></xref> with the message
<xref target="RFC5322"></xref>, which they are authorized to use.  This can be an author's
organization, an operational relay, or one of their agents.  Assertion of
responsibility is validated through a cryptographic signature and by querying
the Signer's domain directly to retrieve the appropriate public key.</t>
<t>DKIM authentication allows domains to create a durable identity to attach
to email. Since its initial proposal it has been widely deployed by
systems sending and receiving email. Receiving services use the DKIM
identity as part of their inbound mail handling, and make delivery
decisions based on the DKIM domain. Email sending services sign customer
email with the customer's own domain, but many also sign with their own
domain.</t>

<section anchor="the-problem"><name>The problem</name>
<t>The presence of a DKIM signature serves as a basis for developing an
assessment of mail received, over time, using that signature.  That
assessment constitutes a reputation, which then serves to guide future
handling of mail arriving with a DKIM signature for that domain name.  The
presence of a validated DKIM signature was designed to ensure that the
developed reputation is the result of activity only by the domain owner, and
not by other, independent parties.  That is, it defines a 'clean' channel of
behavior by the domain owner, with no 'noise' introduced by other actors.</t>
<t>A receiving filtering system contains a rich array of rules and heuristics for
assessing email, for protecting users against spam, phishing, and other
abuses.  DKIM therefore provides an identity that some systems can use for
reputation assessment and prediction of future sender behavior.</t>
<t>During development of the DKIM specification, DKIM Replay was identified as
only of hypothetical concern.  However, that attack has become commonplace,
particularly for systems:</t>

<ul>
<li><t>Attackers create, obtain access, or compromise an account at
some Originator that signs messages with DKIM</t>
</li>
<li><t>Attackers locate a Receiver that consumes DKIM to make a delivery
decision.  If the Receiver uses a reputation system with DKIM for
delivery decisions, the attacker finds an Originator with a high
reputation.</t>
</li>
<li><t>They send an email from that account to an external account also
under their control.</t>
</li>
<li><t>This single message is delivered to the attacker's mailbox,
giving them an email with a valid DKIM signature, for a domain with
high reputation.</t>
</li>
<li><t>They then post the message to a new and large set of additional
recipients at the Receiver.</t>
</li>
</ul>
<t>Internet Mail permits sending a message to addresses that are not
listed in the content To:, Cc: or Bcc: header fields.  Although
DKIM covers portions of the message content, and can cover these
header fields, it does not cover the envelope addresses, used by
the email transport service, for determining handling behaviors.
So this message can then be replayed to arbitrary thousands or
millions of other recipients, none of whom were specified by the
original author.</t>
<t>That is, DKIM Replay takes a message with a valid DKIM signature,
and distributes it widely to many additional recipients, without
breaking the signature.</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Further, a message used in a Replay Attack has the same attributes
as some types of legitimate mail.  That is, an individual, replayed
message has no observable differences from a legitimate message.</li>
</ul>
<t>Therefore, DKIM Replay is impossible to detect or prevent with current
standards and practices.  Simply put, email authentication does not
distinguish benign re-posting flows from a DKIM Replay Attack.</t>
<t>ARC <xref target="RFC8617"></xref> is a protocol to securely propagate authentication results seen
by Mediators that re-post a message, such as mailing lists.  Because ARC is
heavily based on DKIM it has the same &quot;replay&quot; issue as described in section
9.5.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="glossary"><name>Glossary</name>
<t>Modern email operation often involves many actors and many different actions.
This section attempts to identify those relevant to Replay Attacks.</t>
<t>NOTE: This document is only Informative and omits the normative language defined
in <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>. Mail architectural terminology that is
used here is from <xref target="RFC5598"></xref> and <xref target="RFC5321"></xref>.</t>
<t><xref target="RFC5598"></xref> defines mail interactions conceptually from three
perspectives of activities, divided into three types of roles:</t>

<dl>
<dt>Users:</dt>
<dd><t>This includes end-users, but also Mediators that re-post a message after delivery.</t>
</dd>
<dt>Services (Message Handling Service - MHS):</dt>
<dd><t>Moving a message from a single submission to its related delivery.</t>
</dd>
<dt>Administrative (ADministrative Management Domain - ADMD):</dt>
<dd><t>Covering independent operational scope, where functions of authorship, handling, and receiving can take place in any number of different ADMDs.</t>
</dd>
</dl>
<t>Also, as noted in <xref target="RFC5598"></xref>, a given implementation might perform multiple roles.</t>
<t>It is useful to broadly identify participants in mail handling by
functionality as defined in <xref target="RFC5598"></xref> as:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Mail Submission Agent (MSA)</li>
<li>Mail Transmission Agent (MTA)</li>
<li>Mail Delivery Agent (MDA)</li>
</ul>
<t>In addition, a user interacts with the handling service via a:</t>

<ul spacing="compact">
<li>Mail User Agent (MUA).</li>
</ul>
<t>The following is a subset of the Mail Handling Services defined in <xref target="RFC5598"></xref>
to be used in this document.   The are summarized here for convenience:</t>

<dl>
<dt>Originator:</dt>
<dd><t>defined in Section 2.2.1.  This is the first component
of the MHS and works on behalf of the author to ensure the message
is valid for transport; it then posts it to the relay (MTA) that
provides SMTP store-and-forward transfer.  The Originator can DKIM
sign the message on behalf of the author, although it is also
possible that the author's system, or even the first MTA, does DKIM
signing.</t>
</dd>
<dt>Alias:</dt>
<dd><t>defined in Section 5.1.  A type of Mediator user, operating
in between a delivery and a following posting.  The Alias replaces
the original RCPT TO envelope recipient address but does not alter
the content address field header fields.  Often used for Auto-Forwarding.</t>
</dd>
<dt>ReSender:</dt>
<dd><t>as defined in Section 5.2, is a type of Mediator user,
like an Alias; however the ReSender updates the recipient address,
and &quot;splices&quot; the destination header field and possibly other address
fields as well.</t>
</dd>
<dt>Mailing Lists:</dt>
<dd><t>defined in Section 5.3 is another Mediator; it
receives a message and reposts it to the list's members; it might
add list-specific header fields <xref target="RFC4021"></xref> e.g. List-XYZ: might
modify other contents, such as revising the Subject: field, or
adding content to the body.</t>
</dd>
<dt>Receiver:</dt>
<dd><t>defined in Section 2.2.4 is the last stop in the MHS, and
works on behalf of the recipient to deliver the message to their
inbox; it also might perform filtering.</t>
</dd>
</dl>
<t>Any of these actors, as well as those below, can add trace and
operational header fields.</t>
<t>Modern email often includes additional services.  Three that are
relevant to DKIM Replay are:</t>

<dl>
<dt>Email Service Provider (ESP):</dt>
<dd><t>Often called a Bulk Sender - An
originating third-party service, acting as an agent of the author
and sending to a list of recipients.  They may DKIM sign as themselves
and/or sign with the author's domain name.</t>
</dd>
<dt>Outbound Filtering Service:</dt>
<dd><t>Rather than sending directly to
recipients' servers, the Originator can route mail through a Filtering
Service, to provide spam or data loss protection services.  This
service may modify the message and can have a different ADMD from
the Originator.</t>
</dd>
<dt>Inbound Filtering Service:</dt>
<dd><t>The Receiver can also route mail through
a Filtering Service, to provide spam, malware and other anti-abuse
protection services.  Typically, this is done by listing the service
in an DNS MX record.  This service may modify the message and have
a different ADMD from the Receiver.</t>
</dd>
</dl>
<t>The above services can use email authentication as defined in the
following specifications:</t>

<dl>
<dt>DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM):</dt>
<dd><t>Defined in <xref target="RFC6376"></xref>, with a
cryptographic signature that typically survives basic relaying but
can be broken when processed by a Mediator.  Further, DKIM Replay
is defined in RFC6376 section 8.6.</t>
</dd>
<dt>Sender Policy Framework (SPF):</dt>
<dd><t>Defined in <xref target="RFC7208"></xref>, is another
form of message handling authentication that works in parallel to
DKIM and might be relevant to the detection of a DKIM Replay Attack.</t>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="mail-flow-scenarios"><name>Mail Flow Scenarios</name>
<t>The following section categorizes the different mail flows by a
functional description, email authentication and recipient email
header fields.</t>

<section anchor="basic-types-of-flows"><name>Basic types of flows</name>
<t>Direct delivery: In this case, email travels directly from the
author's ADMD or the ADMD of their agent -- to the recipient's ADMD
or their agent.  That is, for origination and reception, any
interesting creation or modification is done by agreement with
either the author or the recipient.  As such, these cases should
have authentication that succeeds.</t>
<t>In this type of flow, SPF is expected to validate.</t>
<t>A DKIM Replay Attack uses a single message, sent through Direct delivery, and repurposes it.</t>

<dl>
<dt>Indirect Delivery:</dt>
<dd><t>This is mail involving a Mediator, producing a
sequence of submission/delivery segments.  While not required, the
Mediator is typically viewed as being in an ADMD that is independent
of the author's ADMD and independent of the recipient's ADMD.</t>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>

<section anchor="direct-examples"><name>Direct examples</name>
<t>ESP: An ESP is authorized to act on behalf of the author and will
originate messages given a message body and a list of recipients,
sending a different message to each recipient.  Content address
fields are typically restricted to just the address of that copy's
recipient.  The mail that is sent is typically 'direct', but the
ESP cannot control whether an address refers to an alias or mailing
list, or the like.  So, the message might become indirect, before
reaching the final recipient.  : The bulk nature of ESP activity
means that it can look the same as DKIM Replay traffic.</t>
<t>Outbound filtering: If the Author's domain has an SPF record that
does not list this filtering service, SPF validation for the author's
domain will fail.  However, the ESP might produce an SPF record of
their own and use their own SMTP MAIL FROM (return) address.</t>

<dl>
<dt>Inbound filtering:</dt>
<dd><t>Typically, an inbound filtering service will
add the results of its analysis to the message.  It might make other
modifications to the message.</t>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>

<section anchor="indirect-examples"><name>Indirect Examples</name>
<t>Indirect mail flows break SPF validation, unless the Mediator is
listed in the SPF record.  This is almost never the case.</t>
<t>Mailing List: The modifications done by a mailing list especially
to the Subject: header field and the body of the message - nearly
always break any existing DKIM signatures.</t>

<dl>
<dt>Alias (e.g., Auto-forwarder):</dt>
<dd><t>Typically, the envelope return (MAIL
FROM) address is replaced, to be something related to the forwarder.
A resender might add trace header fields, but typically does not
modify the recipients or the message body.</t>
</dd>
</dl>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="dkim-replay"><name>DKIM Replay</name>

<section anchor="scenario"><name>Scenario</name>
<t>A spammer will find a mailbox provider with a high reputation and
that signs their message with DKIM.  The spammer sends a message
with spam content from there to a mailbox the spammer controls.
This received message is sometimes updated with additional header
fields such as To: and Subject: that do not damage the existing
DKIM signature, if those fields were not covered by the DKIM
signature.  The resulting message is then sent at scale to target
recipients.  Because the message signature is for a domain name
with a high reputation, the message with spam content is more likely
to get through to the inbox.  This is an example of a spam
classification false negative incorrectly assessing spam to not be
spam.</t>
<t>When large amounts of such spam are sent to a single mailbox provider
-- or through a filtering service with access to data across multiple
mailbox providers -- the operator's filtering engine will eventually
react by dropping the reputation of the original DKIM signer.  Benign
mail from the signer's domain then starts to go to the spam folder.
For the benign mail, this is an example of a spam classification
false positive.</t>
<t>In both cases, mail that is potentially wanted by the recipient
becomes much harder to find, reducing its utility to the recipient
(and the author.)  In the first case, the wanted mail is mixed with
potentially large quantities of spam.  In the second case, the
wanted mail is put in the spam folder.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="direct-flows"><name>Direct Flows</name>
<t>Legitimate mail might have a valid DKIM signature and no associated
SPF record.</t>
<t>So might a Replay attack.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="indirect-flows"><name>Indirect Flows</name>
<t>Example benign indirect flows are outbound and inbound gateway,
mailing lists, and forwarders.  This legitimate mail might have a
valid DKIM signature, and SPF validation that is not aligned with
the content From:</t>
<t>So might a Replay attack.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="replay-technical-characteristics"><name>Replay technical characteristics</name>
<t>A message that has been replayed will typically show these
characteristics:</t>

<ul>
<li><t>Original DKIM signature still validates</t>
</li>
<li><t>Content covered by that signature is unchanged</t>
</li>
<li><t>Received: header fields might be different from the original,
or at least have ones that are added</t>
</li>
<li><t>SMTP Envelope RCTP-TO address will be different</t>
</li>
<li><t>SMTP MAIL-FROM might be different</t>
</li>
<li><t>Replayed mail will typically be sent in very large volume</t>
</li>
<li><t>The original SPF will typically not validate; however if the
MAIL-FROM has been changed to an address controlled by the spammer,
SPF might validate.</t>
</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="basic-solution-space"><name>Basic solution space</name>
<t>As can be seen from the above discussion, there is no straightforward
way to detect DKIM Replay for an individual message, and possibly
nothing completely reliable even in the aggregate.  The challenge,
then, is to look for passive analysis that might provide a good
heuristic, as well as active measures by the author's system to add
protections.</t>
<t>Here are some potential solutions to the problem, and their pros
and cons:</t>

<section anchor="include-the-smtp-rcpt-to-address-in-the-dkim-signature"><name>Include the SMTP RCPT-TO address in the DKIM signature</name>
<t>Since this information is different in the Replay, than it was in
the original sending, locking it into the signature will make
validation fail, if the value has been changed.</t>

<ul>
<li><t>This avoids Replay to destination addresses not anticipated by
the DKIM signer.</t>
</li>
<li><t>Indirect flows will fail, since forwarding involves rewriting
the ENVELOPE-TO; however they already typically fail.</t>
</li>
<li><t>This will detect DKIM Replays, but not distinguish them from all
other forwarding.</t>
</li>
<li><t>If a message has more than one addressee, should the signature
cover all of them, or does this require sending one message per
addressee?  If it covers all of them, note that they might be on
different systems, so that upon arrival, the RCPT-TO list  will not
include all of the original addresses</t>
</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="count-known-dkim-signatures"><name>Count known DKIM signatures</name>
<t>This technique caches known DKIM signatures and counts them.  Those
above a certain threshold is considered DKIM replay.</t>

<ul>
<li><t>Since the same signature is being replayed many times, this might
allow a receiving site with many mailboxes to detect whether a
message is part of a DKIM Replay set, and to then suppress it.</t>
</li>
<li><t>Mailing list traffic, aliases, and the like might also show up
as duplicates.  So this is only an heuristic, and might produce
false positives.</t>
</li>
<li><t>Caches have storage overhead, and uncertain TTLs.</t>
</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="strip-dkim-signatures-on-mailbox-delivery"><name>Strip DKIM signatures on mailbox delivery</name>

<ul>
<li><t>Messages delivered to a mailbox lacking DKIM signatures can no
longer be replayed.</t>
</li>
<li><t>Has no effect when the receiving platform is collaborating with
the bad actor, as the attacker would just avoid stripping the header
fields.</t>
</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="shorten-dkim-signature-key-or-signature-lifetime"><name>Shorten DKIM signature key or signature lifetime</name>

<ul>
<li><t>If the key is no longer available through the DNS, the signature
will no longer validate</t>
</li>
<li><t>Alternatively express a validity period after which the signature
is no longer valid</t>
</li>
<li><t>Unfortunately, bad actors are quite good at taking action very
quickly, and there is a limit to how much the window can be shortened,
if the key is to have any utility for legitimate mail.</t>
</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="add-per-hop-signature-specifying-the-destination-domain"><name>Add Per-hop signature, specifying the destination domain</name>
<t>Distinguish each forwarding hop by its own signature which permits
each forwarding hop to specify the intended next destination ADMD.
That intent can be verified to detect DKIM replay at the Receiver
when the intended ADMD mismatches the current one.</t>

<ul>
<li><t>Messages with this kind of signature cannot be replayed down a
different pathway, since the destination won't match.</t>
</li>
<li><t>Requires every site along the path to support this spec, and to
detect whether the next stop is making a commitment to follow the
spec.</t>
</li>
<li><t>If email goes to a site that does not support this behavior,
traversing a naive forwarder remains indistinguishable from Replay.</t>
</li>
<li><t>The time needed to change a global infrastructure such as email,
to fully support a capability like this in every MTA is essentially
infinite; therefore use of this approach must be narrowly tailored
to scenarios that will adopt it and garner substantial benefit from
it.</t>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations"><name>Security Considerations</name>
<t>This problem statement document has no security considerations.
(Subsequent documents defining changes to DKIM will very likely
introduce new security considerations)</t>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations"><name>IANA Considerations</name>
<t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references><name>Informative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4021.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5321.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5322.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5598.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6376.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7208.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8617.xml"/>
</references>

<section anchor="acknowledgments" numbered="false"><name>Acknowledgments</name>
<t>Thanks goes to Emanuel Schorsch, Evan Burke, Laura Atkins and Murray
Kucherawy for their advice.</t>
</section>

</back>

</rfc>
